(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-02T00:44:25.506759",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
「だからあたしは世界を旅している。『オンガク』を見つけるために」
"That's why I travel the world. To find 'music'."
「そう、この世界線ではそうなのね」
"I see, so that's how it is in this worldline."
「だってうちは……キミのことが大好きだから！」
"Because I... love you so much!"
「わためは非常食、じゃないよー！」
"Watame is not emergency food!"
「きみを見たとき、ピピピときたの！」
"When I saw you, I felt a spark!"
「そういう時はね、ぱ〜っと麦ジュースを飲むに限るかな〜？」
"At times like that, nothing beats downing some cold barley juice!"
「ねえ、気になるなら今からここで私といっしょにやってみる？『ライブ』ってやつをさ」
"Hey, if you're curious, do you want to try a \"live show\" with me right here?"
「君が来るのを待ってたよ。この世界に……『オンガク』を取り戻すことができる君を」
"I was waiting for you. You, who can restore \"music\" to this world."
"I wonder how long it has been since the world became like this."
（どこまでも続く荒野）
"An endless wasteland..."
（木々や植物に侵され崩れた建物）
"...buildings overrun and ruined by trees and plants..."
（砂漠に埋もれ傾く巨大なビル群）
"...and massive skyscrapers buried and tilting in the desert."
（もうずっとずっと前に起きた災厄によって）
"Due to a disaster that happened a long, long time ago..."
（世界は滅びてしまった）
"...the world has perished."
（そんな黄昏を迎えた世界で……）
"In this world that has reached its twilight..."
（「オンガク」を見つけるために）
(To find "music"...)
さ、今日もがんばっていくかー
Well, let's do our best today too.
幾千の
Countless...
儚い鼓動 惜しみなく
...fleeting heartbeats, without regret...
流れる時を追い越して
speeding past the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界
we run through this world.
いくつもの名前と
With so many names
いくつもの身体を
and so many bodies,
使い分けてうまく生きているけど
I use them to survive well, but...
胸の奥痛いよ
deep inside, my chest hurts.
音立てて軋むよ
It creaks loudly...
きっと心、生命、ここにあるから
surely because my heart and life are here.
EXE! 新しい明日へ
EXE! To a new tomorrow!
EXE! 今、漕ぎ出す
EXE! Rowing out now!
EXE! 運命の波間にさらわれたくはない
EXE! I don't want to be swept away by the waves of fate!
幾千の
Countless...
儚い鼓動 惜しみなく
...fleeting heartbeats, without regret...
流れる時を追い越して
speeding past the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界
we run through this world.
I pray among the stars...
わたしはいつも祈ってる
I am always praying.
熱い想いをぶつけたら
If I pour out my passionate feelings,
奇跡さえ起こせるから
I can even make miracles happen!
この景色すべては
This entire scenery
淋しさで出来てる
is made of loneliness.
願うだけで すぐにそばにいられた
Just by wishing, I could be by your side right away.
あの頃の姿を
The shape of those days...
追い求めさまよう
wandering in search of it.
きっと火花、言葉、ここにあるから
Surely because the spark and words are here.
EXE! 懐かしい歌声
EXE! A nostalgic singing voice...
EXE! 今聞こえる
EXE! I can hear it now!
EXE! 真空の中でも受け取れるのはなぜ
EXE! Why can I receive it even in a vacuum?
「通」じあうこのよろこびを感じたい
I want to feel this joy of connecting with you,
場所も時間も飛び越えて
leaping across time and space,
分け合える世代
in a generation sharing with each other.
「信」じあうことがすべてと悟ったよ
I've realized that believing in each other is everything.
君をもう一度見つけたら
Once I find you again,
涙さえ輝くから
even my tears will shine!
幾千の
儚い鼓動 惜しみなく
...fleeting heartbeats, without regret...
流れる時を追い越して
speeding past the flowing time,
駆け抜ける世界
we run through this world.
「通」じ合うこのよろこびを感じたい
I want to feel this joy of connecting with you,
場所も時間も飛び越えて
leaping across time and space,
分け合える世代
in a generation sharing with each other.
「信」じあうことが全てと悟ったよ
I've realized that believing in each other is everything.
君をもう一度みつけたら
Once I find you again,
涙さえ輝くから
even my tears will shine!
もうこの世界には、人はあまり残っていない
There aren't many people left in this world anymore.
文明が崩壊して、インフラも何もかもなくなってしまったのだから、仕方ないことだと思う
Civilization collapsed, and all infrastructure was lost, so I guess it can't be helped.
だけど旅をしていると、何か...
But as I travel, something...
旅をしていると、何かに引き寄せられるように誰かと出会うことがある。
When you are traveling, you sometimes meet someone as if drawn to them by something.
こんな風に。
Just like this.
こんにちは。
Hello there.
こんにちは。あなたは？
Hello. And you are?
私はAZKi。この世界の地図を作りながら
I am AZKi. While drawing a map of this world,
色々なところを調査する「開拓者」をしてるわ。キミは？
I work as a pioneer, surveying various places. What about you?
あたしは旅をしてるんだ。
I am on a journey.
なくなってしまった大切なものを探すために。
To search for something precious that was lost.
大切なもの？
Something precious?
うん。音楽を。
Yes... music.
ふーん。そう、この世界線ではそうなのね。
I see. So in this worldline, that's how it is.
でもあなたは覚えているはずだわ。
But I'm sure you still remember.
ん？
Huh?
記憶にはなくても、
Even if it's not in your memory,
胸の奥の深いところに、いっしょに過ごした時間……
deep down in your heart, the times we spent together...
気持ちを一つにした瞬間を。
The moment our feelings became one.
だってあなたにとってそれは……とても大事なものだったはずだから。
Because to you, that should have been... something very important.
あぁ
Ah...
君が好きな服
The clothes you like
濡れたままだね保存
are still wet, aren't they?
こんな夜だから
Because on a night like this,
響かせてミュージック
make the music echo.
お気に入りの歌は
Your favorite song,
君は知らない
you don't know it.
君だけ知らない
Only you don't know it.
感情論を　君にだけぶつけて
Throwing my emotional arguments only at you,
傷ついたフリしてるけど<
I pretend to be hurt, but...
完全な嘘　いつも言いたいくらい
It's a complete lie, so much that I always want to say it.
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to make sure even more.
ナンセンス？　だけど涙出る
Nonsense? But the tears still flow.
見ないでよ　ひどい顔なの
Don't look, I look awful.
単純だって言われたくないよ
I don't want to be called simple.
もっと確かめてみて
Try to make sure even more.
ねぇ
Hey...
朝が来る前に
Before morning comes,
連れ出しててみ
try taking me out.
こんな夜だから
Because on a night like this,
鳴り止まないミュージック
the music won't stop ringing.
お気に入りの曲は
Your favorite song,
君は踊らない
you won't dance to it.
君だけ踊らない
Only you won't dance.
感情論で　君を傷つけて
Hurting you with emotional arguments,
こんな人　嫌になるでしょ？
You must be getting sick of someone like me, right?
純情なんて　呆れるくらいに
Pure heart? To an amazing degree,
ホント似合わないけど
it really doesn't suit me, but...
テンションちょっと上げて知らんぷり
Raising my spirits a bit and pretending not to care,
困らせたい　そんな気分よ
I want to trouble you, that's just how I feel.
単純だって言われたくないよ
I don't want to be called simple.
きっと我が儘だけど
I'm surely selfish, but...
完全少女論
Complete Girl Theory,
自己中心論
Egocentrism Theory,
気分上々論
Feeling Great Theory,
そういいんじゃない？
Isn't that fine?
感情暴走論
Emotion Runaway Theory,
リカバリ不可能論
Irrecoverable Theory,
一苦労でしょ？
It's a lot of trouble, isn't it?
ほんのちょっと手を伸ばして
Just stretch your hand out a little bit.
きっと全然気づかない
You surely won't notice at all.
笑い合うよ　朝が来たら
We'll laugh together when morning comes.
大丈夫だから
Because it'll be alright.
感情論を　君に投げつけて
Hurting you with emotional arguments,
演じてるフリしてるけど
I pretend to be acting, but...
完全そうそう　いつも言いたいくらい
Completely, yes, so much that I always want to say it.
君は優しすぎるけど
You are way too kind, but...
感情論も　君に投げつけて
Hurling emotional arguments at you too,
傷ついたフリしてるけど
I pretend to be hurt, but...
完全そうそう　いつも言いたいくらい
Completely, yes, so much that I always want to say it.
もっと確かめてみる
I'll try to make sure even more.
(……)
(......)
(さっきのは……なんだったんだろう)
(What was that... just now?)
(たくさんの人たちと、)
(Surrounded by so many people...)
(その人たちが発する熱気に包まれて、あたしはすごくワクワクしてた)
(...and wrapped in their excitement, I was so thrilled.)
(なんだかすごく懐かしい感じがした……)
(It felt somehow so nostalgic...)
"ねえねえ、キミ、大丈夫？"
"Hey, are you okay?"
"え？"
"Eh?"
"なんか顔色がよくなかったからさ。"
"You didn't look very well."
"あ、うちはミオだよ。占い師をやってる。"
"Oh, I'm Mio. I'm a fortune teller."
"お、キミ、何かを探してるね。そう占いにでてる。"
"Oh, you're looking for something. That's what my fortune says."
"わかるの？"
"You can tell?"
"うん。よかったら話してみて。"
"Yeah. If you'd like, try talking to me."
"何か力になれるかもしれないし。"
"Maybe I can be of help."
"実は――"
"Actually—"
"なるほど――キミは「オンガク」を探してるんだね。"
"I see... So you're looking for \"music.\""
"それなら、あそこに行ってみればいいんじゃない？"
"In that case, why don't you try going there?"
"世界の果てにあるっていう、光の塔。"
"The Tower of Light, which is said to be at the end of the world."
"そこには「天使」が住んでて、やって来た人の願いを叶えてくれるんだって。"
"An \"angel\" lives there, and she grants the wishes of those who visit."
"だからそこに行ってお願いをすれば、キミの探しものも見つかるんじゃないかな。"
"So if you go there and make a wish, maybe you'll find what you're looking for."
"親切にありがとう。そこに行ってみることにするよ！"
"Thanks for your kindness. I'll decide to go there!"
"どういたしまして。でもお礼なんていらないって。"
"You're welcome. But I told you, no thanks are necessary."
"？"
"?"
"だってうちは――キミのことが大好きだから！"
"Because I... really love you!"
"ずっとずっと前からね！"
"From way, way back!"
[曲名] コトダマ紡ぐ未来 / 作詞：石川泰 作曲：田辺トシノ
"[Song] Kotodama Tsumugu Mirai / Lyrics: Yasushi Ishikawa, Composition: Toshino Tanabe"
遥か 遠く
Far... in the distance...
続く 果てなき道
...this endless road continues on.
それでも いつか
Even so, someday...
たどり着くと信じて
...believing that I will reach it.
たとえ 今は
Even if, for now...
辛く 厳しくても
...it is painful and harsh,
小さな 笑顔
...a tiny smile...
守る 全て捧げて
...I will protect it, giving my everything.
心 重なる
Our hearts overlap...
言葉より強い絆に
...into a bond stronger than words.
染め上げてゆく
We will color ourselves...
一つになるコトバで
...with the word that makes us one.
記憶たどる 追憶の旅
Tracing back memories, a journey of recollection...
続けて
...continues.
あらゆることを 受け止めるから
Since I will accept everything...
言葉はいらないの
...no words are needed anymore.
それは永遠に
That is for eternity.
いつも 近く
Always close...
そばで見つめていたけど保存
...I was watching over you from your side, but...
気づかず いても
...even if you didn't notice...
今は 遠く感じる
...now I feel so far away.
あとを 追いかけ
Chasing after you...
絆から愛に変われば"
...if our bond turns into love,
染め上げてゆく
We will color ourselves completely...
二人だけの秘密"
...with a secret meant only for the two of us.
思いを込めた 言葉の強さ
The strength of words infused with feelings...
信じ
...believing in them...
...信じてる
...believing.
口にした時 覚悟していた
When I spoke it, I was prepared.
未来を紡ぐために
In order to spin the future.
気がつけばほら
Before I knew it, look...
心に宿る
...lodged in my heart,
ともしび
...is a light.
小さな光
If our tiny lights...
寄り添い合えば
...draw close together,
その未来を指して
...they will point to that future.
青く広がる
Spreading out in blue,
晴れ渡る空
is the clear sky.
見上げる
We look up at it.
もう言葉すら
Because we no longer
いらないから
even need words,
ただ 抱きしめていた
just hold each other tight.
時は 永遠に
Time will go on forever.
（降り注ぐ 雨のような歓声）
(Cheers raining down like rain.)
（その中で、きらびやかな服を着たあたしは、幸せそうな笑顔で手を振っている）
(Among them, dressed in brilliant clothes, I wave with a happy smile.)
（まるで、もう一人のあたしのように）
(Just like another me.)
（世界の果てにあるという光の塔）
(The Tower of Light, said to be at the end of the world.)
（「オンガク」を探すために、あたしはそこを目指すことに決めた）
(To find "Music," I decided to head there.)
（何日かかるかわからないけど、幸いなことに時間はたくさんある）
(I don't know how many days it will take, but fortunately, I have plenty of time.)
（ただ……）
(But...)
お腹、空いた……
I'm hungry...
なんでわためを見てお腹を鳴らしてるの！？
Why is your stomach growling while looking at Watame?!
え、わからないけど、何かキミを見たら急に
Eh, I don't know, but looking at you just suddenly made me...
わためは非常食じゃないよー！
Watame is not emergency food!
見逃してくれたら、代わりにわためが歌うから～
If you spare me, Watame will sing instead!
……ウタ？
...Sing?
ウタって……なに？
What is... singing?
え、キミ、歌を知らないの？
Eh? You don't know what singing is?
よーし、じゃあ、わためが教えてあげるよ、歌っていうのはね～
Alright! Then Watame will teach you. Singing is...
滅びていくこのステラ
This stella is perishing,
絆を辿るストーリー
A story tracing our bonds.
受け継ぐ想いが
May the thoughts passed down
生まれ変われますように
be reborn anew.
breath of stella
[Title: breath of stella]
目の前
Before me,
現れた無表情は
an expressionless face appeared.
誰にも
Showing affection
懐を見せないまま
to no one.
事象が
Phenomena
世界を歪ませて
distorted the world,
光が
And the light
ただ眩しすぎた
was simply too dazzling.
燦々と照りつける
Scorching brilliantly,
荒野に残した足跡
the footprints left in the wasteland.
与えられたのなら
If it was given to me,
守るものだけ
only what must be protected.
滅びていくこのステラ
This stella is perishing,
叶うことがないとしても
even if it will never come true.
変えよう
Let's change
世界を
the world,
灯していく
lighting the way.
震える手が弾いた
A trembling hand pulled back
意味を持たない銃口
the meaningless muzzle of a gun.
輝く
Beneath
星の下
the shining stars,
わたしは今息をする
I am breathing right now.
それなら
If so,
あなたは騙したんだ
you deceived me.
今なら
If it's now...
全て分かってしまう
I understand everything...
名前を
Even if you
呼んでくれていても
were calling my name,
私に
it was not
向けられていなかった
directed at me.
消える日の前でただ
Just standing still before the day of disappearance,
立ち尽くして煙る灰
the smoldering ashes.
命の理屈が今
The logic of life now
答えを迫る
demands an answer.
滅びていくその中で
Within that decaying world,
息を切らしたバトルクライ保存
a breathless battle cry.
崩れた絆を保存
Shaking off
振りほどいて
the shattered bonds,
お願いどうかそばにいて
please, somehow stay by my side.
声が重星に求めた
My voice pleaded to the binary stars.
終わりと始まりの
Within the time of the end
時のなかで
and the beginning...
ああ
Ah...
瞳の奥に澄んだ
Clear in the depths of your eyes...
壊れかけている心の荷物
the baggage of a heart on the verge of breaking.
引き金にかけた指
The finger placed on the trigger...
先が示す未来を祈るだろう
will probably pray for the future it points to.
滅びてゆくこのステラ
This Stella that is decaying,
瞬きの数の傷
scars as numerous as the blinks of an eye.
心がこのまま途絶えてしまっても
Even if my heart ceases like this,
私の生まれた理由も保存
the reason for my birth,
手放さないでお願い
please don't let it go.
終わりと始まりの
Within the time of the end
時のなかで
and the beginning...
ああ
Ah...
私はここにいるよ
I am right here.
何度も確かめられるよ
We can confirm it as many times as it takes.
そう、心の存在と名前を
Yes, the existence and name of the heart.
あなたが生き抜いた世界は
The world you survived
まだ私の中で息をする
still breathes inside of me.
（光、光、光）
(Light, light, light...)
（その星のようなきらめきが――頭に焼きついて離れない）
(That star-like brilliance is burned into my mind and won't leave.)
（あの子がやっていたことはなんだったんだろう？）
(What was it that she was doing?)
（「ウタ」だって言ってたけど……初めて聞く言葉だ）
(She called it a "song," but... it's a word I've heard for the first time.)
（だけど「ウタ」は、あたしの心の深いところに確かに染み込んできた……）
(But that "song" definitely soaked deep into my heart...)
静かだなー……
"It's so quiet..."
（この世界は、ずっと静寂に包まれている）
(This world is always wrapped in silence.)
（だけどさっきのあれは――「ウタ」は、そのどれとも違った）
(But that thing from earlier—that "song"—was different from any of that.)
（あれは、なんだったんだろう……）
(What was that, I wonder...)
（あと別れ際にくれたこの頭につける道具は……？ 遺物……？）
(And what is this tool for my head that she gave me when we parted...? A relic...?)
（確か「ヘッドセット」って言ってた）
(I think she called it a "headset.")
（これを使えば……あたしも「ウタ」えるんだろうか）
(If I use this... will I be able to "sing" too?)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
it's time to move on,保存
forever has gone
two eyes in the face of billions of voices
I saw the flashing lights move further in the distance
(dream was not meant to be)
and outside these walls that I have created
the sound of stars colliding
echoes in the distance
and dreams they shatter
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
renew... the light...
the dream...
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory (Ah)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
(time to move on)
(it's time to move on,)
forever has gone
(time to move on)
(it's time to move)
(it's time to move on)
(time to move on)
(it's time to move)
and outside these walls that I have created
the sound of stars colliding
echoes in the distance
and dreams they shatter
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
let it break into a thousand pieces
let the wind blow it all away
dreams are fragile but our hearts grow
stronger from the memories...
renew... the light... the dream...
forever has gone,
today is infinity
and yesterday's dreams,
today a faint memory (Ah)
forever has gone,
today is infinity
it's time to move on,
forever has gone
(time to move on)
(it's time to move)
(it's time to move on)
(time to move on)
(it's time to move)
「ウタ」を知ってから、数日が経った。
A few days have passed since I learned about "Song."
旅路は進み、ようやく光の塔がおぼろげながらに見えてくる。
My journey continued, and at last, the Tower of Light faintly came into view.
だけど「オンガク」や「ウタ」について知っている人は、ほとんどいなかった。
But there was almost no one who knew anything about "music" or "song."
もしかしたらあたしは、ないものねだりをしているだけなのかもしれない。
Perhaps I am simply wishing for the impossible.
でも……新しい出会いはあった。
But... there was a new encounter.
Ciaooo! I'm Raora Panthera!
Ciao! I'm Raora Panthera!
あたし「絵描き」をやってるんだ！
I'm an artist!
きみを見たとき、ビビッときたの！「きみにはこれが似合いそう！」
When I saw you, it just clicked! "This would look so good on you!"
さらさらさら……っと
*scribble scribble...*
はい、プレゼント！
Here's a present for you!
プレゼント！
Present!
これ……あたし？
Is this... me?
うん、ステージ衣装を着た、キミの絵！So cute……！
Yes! A drawing of you in your stage outfit! So cute...!
ちょ、ちょっとあたしにはかわいすぎない？
Isn't it... a bit too cute for me?
そんなことないよー！すっごくぴったり！
That's not true! It fits you perfectly!
そ、そうかな……？
Y-You think so...?
きみはこのステージ衣装を着て……
Wear this stage outfit and...
Let's sing with me!!
YEAH~
The knacks of surviving in this world
are being human and being right
Everyone keeps telling me to grow up fast
And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Your unfair rules
Ego trip into a loop
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving
Getting through anything
Stay alive
Hated ones Naked hearts
Worthless games that never end
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて何が間違っているんだ
What is right, and what is wrong?
僕はただ
I just...
ここで生きてると叫びたいだけ
want to scream that I am alive right here
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!!
YEAH~
Everyone wanna choose the right path only
They would seek salvation in this closed world
Filthy hands and mind never get clean again though
And it is so tough, can't wrap my head around it
Cannot turn the clock back
Cannot take a turn back
We do belong nowhere in this world
Yet we are surviving
Getting through anything
Stay alive
Missing piece Warmth of hands
Joys and even stabbing pains
Found them in the darkness in the end
何が正しくて何が間違っているんだ
What is right, and what is wrong?
誰だって
No matter who we are,
ここで生きてると叫んでいるのに
we are all screaming that we are alive right here, yet...
Facing what they really want to do,
They'll make it at the cost of everything
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!!
YEAH~
また失って もう嫌になって
Losing again, I've had enough of it...
それでも消えなくて
...and yet, it won't disappear.
その心の名をなんと言うのだろう
I wonder what we should call the name of this heart.
僕はここで今叫んでいるんだよ
I am screaming right here, right now!
君だって
And you, too,
ここで同じように叫んでいるんだろう
are probably screaming the same way here!
I heard voices calling out my true name
I will never give up or be swayed anymore
Nobody can stop me
This is the way I am
I'll EXECUTE you, drop dead baby!!
YEAH~
So, this is the way I am
色とりどりのかわいらしい『衣装』
A colorful, lovely outfit...
（それは不思議とぴったりと身体に馴染んでいた）
(It felt strangely snug and fit my body perfectly.)
（『衣装』を身にまとい、『ヘッドセット』をつけて、『歌う』あたし）
(Dressed in my outfit, wearing a headset, singing—that's me.)
（あっちのあたしと、今のあたし、どっちが本物なんだろう）
(The me back then, and the me now... I wonder which one is real.)
そういう時はね、難しいことは忘れてぱぁ～っと楽しいことをするに限るかぬぁ～？
In times like that, it's best to forget the hard stuff and do something completely fun!
クレープを焼いたりとか、アロマで癒されたりとか
Like baking crepes, relaxing with aromatherapy,
ベリーダンスを踊ったりとかして気持ちよくなれば、悩み事なんてどこかに飛んでいっちゃうものなんだよ
or doing some belly dancing to feel good... then all your worries will just fly away!
そういうものなの？
Is that really how it works?
うん、そういうものかぬぁ～
Yep, that's exactly how it is!
だって世の中のだいたいのことは、それがどう見えるかぬぁっていうのは見る人次第なんだから
Because most things in this world depend entirely on the perspective of the person looking.
たとえばアキローゼのこの格好が、芸術的に見えるかセクシーに見えるかをあなたたち次第
For example, whether Akirose's outfit here looks artistic or sexy is entirely up to you.
みたいにね？うふふ
Don't you think? Hehehe.
え、あ、うん
Uh, oh, yeah...
そうだ！せっかくこうして出会えたんだから、いっしょに踊ろっか？
I know! Since we've finally met like this, why don't we dance together?
あなたとアキローゼの二人で
Just you and Akirose, the two of us.
え、でもあたし、踊ったことなんてないんだけど
Wait, but I've never danced before...
だいじょうぶだいじょうぶ、これはあなたのためだけに考えた、“踊り子アキローゼの振り付け”だから
It's totally fine! This choreography was created by 'Dancer Akirose' just for you.
ね？
Right?
とある竜の恋の歌
[Song: A Certain Dragon's Love Song]
踊る舞い立つ大地に
On the dancing, soaring earth,
恋の歌響けば
When the song of love echoes,
狂いだす歯車
The gears begin to turn madly,
止められぬ定めが
An unstoppable destiny
弾けた
Has burst forth.
よみがえる今
Now, awakening,
古にしえより
from ancient times,
世紀末の恋
a love at the end of the century
目覚めた
has awakened.
絆を求めて
Seeking a bond,
炎はほとばしる
the flames gush forth.
破壊と再生
Destruction and rebirth,
気高き君の気迫
your noble, powerful spirit.
透き通る魂
A transparent soul,
嘘のない気高く
honest and noble,
限界を抱えて
facing our limits,
未熟な恋持つ
carrying an immature love,
愚かさ包み
wrapping around our foolishness,
月灯り今
The moonlight now,
二人照らす
shines upon the two of us.
つかの間の
A fleeting moment
時重ねた
where our times overlapped.
絆の行方を
The destination of our bond,
両手で抱きしめた
I held it tight with both hands.
終わりと始まり
An ending and a beginning,
尊き君の記憶
your precious memories.
歪むの 求める
Warping, seeking...
踊るは 音 走る
Dancing to the running sound,
破壊と 再生
destruction and rebirth,
気高き 君の呪縛
the spell of noble you.
歪むの 行方を
The whereabouts of the warp,
両手で 抱きしめた
I embraced with both hands.
終わりと 始まり
The end and the beginning,
尊き 君の記憶
your precious memories.
(どこか懐かしいだれかと出会う度に、頭に浮かぶ映像が鮮明になってくる)
(Every time I meet someone strangely familiar, the images floating in my mind become clearer.)
(もう少しで……何かがわかりそうな気がした)
(I felt like, just a little more... and I would understand something.)
それって、「ライブ」なんじゃないかな？
Isn't that a "live concert"?
「ライブ」？
A live concert?
うん、そう。私、旅芸人だから噂で聞いたことがあるんだけど、「オンガク」があった頃にはよく開催されてたんだって。
Yeah, exactly. I'm a traveling performer, so I've heard rumors about it. Back when "music" existed, they were held often.
うーん……
Hmm...
(そうだ、あたしは「ライブ」をやっていたんだ――)
(That's right... I was doing live concerts...)
ねえ、気になるなら今からここで私と一緒にやってみる？
Hey, if you're curious, do you want to try doing one with me right here, right now?
え？
Eh?
ていうかやろうよ！あなたとならやってみたい！
I mean, let's do it! I want to try it with you!
――「ライブ」ってやつを！
—That "live concert" thing!
とおくできこえる
Hearing from afar,
わたしをよぶこえ
a voice calling me.
あなたのなみだの
The reason for your tears...
りゆうをしってたはずなのに
...I should have known it, and yet.
かわくまえに
Before it dries,
かれるまえに
before it withers,
すべてささげようと
I will offer everything...
あなたにだけ
...only to you.
なにをもとめるのか
What is it that I seek?
だれをあいするのかさえ わからず
Without even knowing who to love,
はいのようにくちていくこころに
In my heart decaying like ash,
あなたのかけらだけは
only fragments of you remain.
てさぐりでもかたちをなぞれば
If I trace your shape, even if fumbling,
ながいねむりのなか
inside this long sleep...
あなたをゆめみるでしょう
...I will surely dream of you.
ふたり みなれたあの日々を何度でも
We'll recall those familiar days over and over.
よあけは あなたにだけ
The dawn is only for you,
そらには もうはてがないから
because the sky has no end anymore.
なにをもとめたのか
What did I seek?
とおいひのわたしにいまといかけ
I ask my past self of distant days.
くだかれ いろあせ おちていく
Shattered, faded, and falling away,
あのかけらたちはどこへ
where did those fragments go?
Where did those fragments go...
手探りでも かたちを なぞった
Fumbling around, I traced the shape...
長い夢の中で いま
...within this long dream, now...
あなたと また出会えた
...I was able to meet you again.
ふたり 願ったこの瞬間を最後まで
Until the end of this moment we both wished for...
広がる 青い空が
...the sprawling blue sky...
あなたを いつでも見てるから
...will always be watching over you.
（光の塔はもう目の前に迫っていた）
(The Tower of Light was already looming before my eyes.)
（それにつれて、頭に浮かぶ映像はさらに鮮明になってきていた）
(Along with that, the images in my head were becoming even clearer.)
（まるで夢から覚めるように）
(Like waking up from a dream...)
（まるでそれが本物であるかのように）
(...as if it were the real thing.)
（ーー『ライブ』をしていた場所が）
(—the place where we held the "live" concert...)
･･･着いた
...We're here.
ここが･･･光の塔
So this is... the Tower of Light.
塔っていうよりも、何かの舞台みたいにも見えるな
Rather than a tower, it looks more like some kind of stage.
似てる･･･気がする。あの、『ライブ』をやっていた場所に
It feels... similar to that place where we held the "live" concert.
いらっしゃい、ライオンさん
Welcome, Lion-san.
キミが･･･願いを叶えてくれる天使？
Are you... the angel who will grant my wish?
うん、そう。キミが来るのを待ってたよ
Yes, that's right. I've been waiting for you to come.
この世界に･･･『オンガク』を取り戻すことができるキミを
For you, who can restore "music" to this world.
『オンガク』を･･･あたしが･･･？
"Music"... by me...?
そうだよ
Yes, indeed.
ここに来るまでにたくさんのものを受け取ったキミは、もう『オンガク』が何か分かってるんじゃないかな？
Having received so many things on your way here, I think you already know what "music" is, don't you?
ほら、ボクと一緒に飛ぼうーー
Come, let's fly together—
囚われた切望の淵で 私を抱きしめてください
In the depths of captive yearning, please embrace me.
静寂に埋め尽くされて
Completely buried in silence,
独りで凍えてる
...I am freezing all alone.
崩れ落ちていく 楽園の果てで
Crumbling down at the end of paradise,
忘れられた祈りが響いてる
...a forgotten prayer echoes.
支配する闇の中でも
Even within the dominating darkness,
枯れない
...never withering...
愛よ目覚めよ 永久に
...awake, oh love, for eternity!
無限に降る孤独を
The infinitely falling loneliness,
その指で染めてください
...please stain it with your fingers.
叫ぶこの心が
So that this screaming heart...
哀しみを愛せるように
...can learn to love the sadness.
まだ見ぬ あの光の景色へ
To that yet-unseen scenery of light.
乱れ咲く花より深く 優しく口づけてください
Deeper than a profusely blooming flower, please kiss me gently.
ためらいの吐息さえも
Even the hesitant sighs...
命
...and life...
お伴してく
I will accompany you
虹の幻に
into the rainbow's illusion.
祝宴の鐘を
Let the celebratory bells ring,
その温もり　双眸に伝うまで
until that warmth reaches our eyes.
ほとばしる
Surging forward
嵐の中も
even in the midst of the storm,
止まない
never-ending...
愛を目覚めよ
Awaken, my love!
抗えぬ　願いを
Please cherish and welcome
そら愛でて迎えてください
this irresistible wish.
出逢えた歓びに
With a naked heart
震えてる裸の心で
shivering with the joy of meeting you,
求める
I seek...
のは残酷な彼方へ
the cruel yonder.
こぼれ散る涙が
When the spilling tears
キラキラと風に舞う頃
dance sparkling in the wind,
絆は痛みを下さい
let our bond bring me pain,
永遠に消えないように
so that it will never disappear.
無限に降る孤独を
Please entrust me
私に預けてください
with the endlessly falling loneliness.
呼び合えた心が
Our hearts that called to each other
扉を放ち羽ばたく
will unlock the door and soar.
近づくあの始まりの園へ
We draw closer to that garden of beginnings.
数時間前、露天商
[A few hours ago, at a street stall]
へー、この街の露店は品揃えがいいな。
Wow, the street stalls in this town have a great selection.
他では見ない珍しいものがいっぱいある。
There are so many rare things you don't see elsewhere.
旅を続けてると、やっぱりどうしても装備品は必要になってくるからなあ……
When you keep traveling, you always end up needing gear, after all...
ちょっと覗いていこう。
Let's take a quick look.
あ、これいいな。「ブランケットインクッション」
Oh, this is nice! A 'blanket-in-cushion'.
ブランケットなのに袋に収納すればクッションにもなるから、
Even though it's a blanket, it becomes a cushion when packed in its bag,
これがあればどこでも一休みできて、旅のお供にぴったりかも。
so with this, I can rest anywhere. It might be perfect for traveling.
コンパクトなのにふかふかで、寝心地もよさそう。
It's compact yet fluffy, and looks really comfy to sleep on.
収納袋の絵もいい感じ。
The drawing on the storage bag is also nice.
こっちは何だろう？
What's this one?
「SSRBミニウォレット」か……
An 'SSRB Mini Wallet'...
買い物をしたり、小物を収納するのに財布は必需品なんだよね。
A wallet is a must-have for shopping and storing small items.
小銭もお札も入れられるっていうのも嬉しいな。
It's also great that it can hold both coins and bills.
今使ってるのも古くなってきたし、そろそろ買い替えてもいいかも。
The one I'm using now is getting old, so maybe it's time to replace it.
お、この「ブレスレット」、かっこいい。
Oh, this bracelet is cool!
デザインが馴染みやすいから普段使いしやすそうだし、ライオンの加護もついてるんだー。
The design blends in easily, making it great for everyday use, and it even has a lion's blessing!
これを着けてたら君もライオンになれるかも？なーんて。
If you wear this, maybe you can become a lion too? Just kidding!
ふふ、これかわいいな。ヘルメット被ってる。
Hehe, this is cute. It's wearing a helmet.
「SSRBぬいぐるみキーホルダー」……着けてるだけですっごい楽しい気分になれそう。
An 'SSRB Plushie Keychain'... Just having it on seems like it'd cheer me up.
手のひらサイズのちょうどいい大きさだから、バックパックにぶら下げてもいいし、ベルトに留めるのとかもありかな。
It's the perfect palm-sized size, so hanging it on a backpack or clipping it to a belt would work too.
これも買い物候補っと。
Adding this to my shopping list too.
どうしよう、全部欲しい……
What should I do? I want them all...
どれにするか迷う……
I can't decide which one to get...
え、これを全部まとめたセットもあるんだ？
Eh? There's a set that has all of them together?
しかもそれだと、収納袋の絵を描いてるトマリ先生の描き下ろしのポストカードと直筆サイン、箔押しメッセージが特典でついてくるのか。
What's more, that set comes with a special bonus: an exclusive postcard illustrated by Tomari-sensei, along with a handwritten signature and a foil-stamped message!
うーん……
Hmm...
セットでください。
I'll take the set, please.
やっとわかった気がする。
I think I finally understand.
AZKi、みこ、わため……
AZKi, Miko, Watame...
ラオーラ、アキロゼ、リオナ……
Raora, Akirose, Riona...
かなた……そしてこの舞台に向けて声援を送ってくれていたたくさんのみんな
Kanata... and everyone who sent their cheers to this stage.
みんなから受け取ったたくさんのもの――そこに込められた想い
Everything I received from everyone—the feelings within them.
それらが集まって……「オンガク」になる
They gather together... and become 'music'.
新しいあたしが生まれるんだ
A new me is being born.
うん、キミならそう言ってくれると思った
Yeah, I knew you'd say that.
そんなキミに僕から、僕たちから……最後に「曲」を送るよ
To you, from me, from us... we send you one last song.
今日という素敵な日の最後を飾る……新しい獅白ぼたんの誕生を祝う、世界で一つだけの「曲」
To crown the end of this wonderful day... a unique song in the world to celebrate the birth of a new Shishiro Botan.
今のキミなら歌えるはず。「音楽」を――取り戻せるはずだから
The current you should be able to sing it. You should be able to... take back 'music'.
がおってこ！
[Song: Gaotteko!]
がおってこ！ がおってこ！ がおってこ！ がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Ga otte ko, ga otte ko, ga otte ko, ga otte ko, ga otte ko!
15分早起きした
I woke up 15 minutes early
奇跡的な起床記録
A miraculous waking record
珍しい誇らしい朝
A rare, proud morning
誰のせいでしょうか
I wonder whose fault it is?
きみのがおが聴こえると
When I hear your roar
気がするだけかもしれないけど
It might just be my imagination, but
無敵になる気がして
It makes me feel invincible
走って 走って 走れんだ
It makes me run, run, run
Shine on! どこ？って迷っちゃっても
(Shine on!) Even if I get lost, asking 'where?'
Ride on! 合図は遠くの声
(Ride on!) The signal is a voice from afar
Vibe on! 迎えに行くよ
(Vibe on!) I'll come to get you
We're Lions!!
We're lions, oh-oh-oh-oh
Shine on! きみがいる世界が
(Shine on!) The world you're in
Ride on! 輝く合言葉
(Ride on!) Is the shining password
がおっていいヤツみんなで
With all the good folks who roar
Everybody, say 1-2-3!!
Everybody, say, 'One, two, three!'
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Ga otte ko, ga otte ko
ひとりじゃないって魔法をかけたら
If I cast a spell that says 'you're not alone'
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Ga otte ko, ga otte ko
不安にだって一緒に吠えて
We'll even roar at our anxieties together
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Ga otte ko, ga otte ko
笑顔でバフかけちゃえるから
Because we can buff each other with smiles
がおってこ！ がおってこ！
Ga otte ko, ga otte ko
ここがそう 私達の最高
Right here, this is our very best
Rawr rawr!! Yeah! Rawr rawr!! Yeah!
Rawr, rawr, rawr, rawr, yeah! Rawr, rawr, rawr, rawr, yeah!
一日一獅子 Motivation
One lion a day, motivation
低めのやる気がおで上昇
My low motivation rises with a roar
Join us my peeps! 百獣で優勝
Join us my peeps, let's win as the king of beasts
だからがおっていきましょう
So let's all roar together
靴ずれした右足が
My right foot with a blister
今日のやる気を持っていった
Took away my motivation for today
椅子の角っこが小指も
The corner of a chair also
ついでにしばいてくれた
Decided to strangle my pinky toe for good measure
きみのがおが聴こえると
When I hear your roar
それとも、ライブをしてるあたしの方が、今のあたしが見てる夢……？
Or is the me who is performing the live... the dream that the current me is seeing...?
胡蝶の夢って知ってる？
Do you know about the "Butterfly Dream"?
君の言う通り、この世界はもしかしたら、もう一人の君が見ている夢なのかもしれないし、
As you say, this world might be a dream that another you is seeing...
もしかしたらさっきまで君が見ていた「ライブ」こそが、この世界の君が見ている夢かもしれない。
Or maybe the "live" you were watching just now is the dream that you in this world are seeing.
もしかしたらいつか訪れる未来なのかもしれないし、観測された違う世界線を垣間見てるだけなのかもしれない。
Or perhaps it's a future that will arrive someday... Or we might just be glimpsing a different observed timeline.
世界は不確定なんだよ。
The world is uncertain, you know.
「オンガク」は、そんなたくさんの世界を繋ぐ糸みたいなもの。
Music is like a thread that connects all those different worlds.
数え切れないほど存在する可能性の中で、それでも「オンガク」だけはいつだってそこにあるものなの。
Among the countless possibilities that exist, only music is always there.
うちたちが、ぼたんのこと想う気持ちもね！
Just like our feelings for you, Botan!
わため、どこにいてもぼたんちゃんのことが大好きだよぉ！
Watame will always love you, Botan-chan, no matter where she is!
ぼたん先輩の絵、また描きたいなー！
I want to draw Botan-senpai again!
ふふ、ししろんと同じ時間をのんびり過ごすの、アキロゼはすごく好きかな。
Hehe, Akirose really loves spending time relaxing together with Shishiron.
ぼたん先輩、いつかは私と一緒にまた歌ってほしいです。
Botan-senpai, I hope you'll sing with me again someday.
でも、その前に……
But before that...
せーの、誕生日おめでとう！
One, two, happy birthday!
みんな……。ありがとう。
Everyone... Thank you.
みんなの気持ち、送ってくれたお祝いの言葉……確かに受け取ったよ。
I've truly received everyone's feelings and birthday wishes.
すごく……すごくうれしい。
I'm really... really happy.
今ならきっと、前だけを見て走っていられる。
Now, I'm sure I can keep running forward.
これからも、新しい世界に、まだ見たことのないたくさんの可能性に、挑戦することができる！
I can continue to challenge new worlds and many possibilities I've never seen before!
だってここが……あたしたちの最高だから！
Because this place... is our absolute best!
だから、この先も一緒に行こう！
So let's keep going forward together!
次に生まれるのが、どんな世界でも！
No matter what world is born next!
みんなのこと、本当に、本当に大好きだよ！
I really, truly love you all!
（次にあたしが生まれるのは、どこなんだろう）
(Where will I be born next?)
（でもそれが、どこでも大丈夫）
(But wherever it is, it'll be fine.)
（さよならは言わない）
(I won't say goodbye.)
（きっとあたしは、この幸せな物語を胸に、どこまでだって飛べるはずだから）
(Because I'm sure I can fly anywhere with this happy story in my heart.)
（そこに「音楽」と、みんなからもらった温かくて、優しい想いがあれば！）
(As long as there is "music" and the warm, kind feelings I received from everyone!)
（次の世界で、また会おう……！）
(Let's meet again in the next world...!)
（きみがいる世界で……！）
(In the world where you are...!)
▶ 新しい世界に旅立つ？
▶ Depart to a new world?
（だからあたしは世界を旅している）
(That's why I'm traveling the world)
たとえどこにいたとしても、それは……とても大事なことだったはずだから
No matter where you were, that must have been... very important
よーし、あたしの歌で癒してあげるよ。歌っていうの魔法……
Alright, I'll heal you with my song. Songs are magic...
だってうち……ぼたんのことが大好きだから！
Because I... really love Botan!
Let's try! ぼたん先輩！
Let's try! Botan-senpai!
Let's draw with us!
だいたいあなたって子は！これ、あなたのためにしたんだからね。
Why are you like this! I did this for you, you know.
「嘘」すら、あれは優しさの「嘘」なんだから
Even that "lie" was a "lie" of kindness.
うん！いつまでも待ってるよ。
Yeah! I'll wait forever.
みんなのこと、本当に、本当に大好きだよ！
I really, truly love you all!
MUST & RELIVE